<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "http://jats.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/1.0/JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd">
<!--<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="article.xsl"?>-->
<article article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.0" xml:lang="en"
    xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
    <front>
        <journal-meta>
            <journal-id journal-id-type="issn">2376-6832</journal-id>
            <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>Collabra</journal-title>
            </journal-title-group>
            <issn pub-type="epub">2376-6832</issn>
            <publisher>
                <publisher-name>University of California Press</publisher-name>
            </publisher>
        </journal-meta>
        <article-meta>
            <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1525/collabra.18</article-id>
            <article-categories>
                <subj-group>
                    <subject>Original research report</subject>
                </subj-group>
            </article-categories>
            <title-group>
                <article-title>Implicit Preferences for Straight People over Lesbian Women and Gay
                    Men Weakened from 2006 to 2013</article-title>
            </title-group>
            <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                    <name>
                        <surname>Westgate</surname>
                        <given-names>Erin C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <email>ecw4za@virginia.edu</email>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                    <name>
                        <surname>Riskind</surname>
                        <given-names>Rachel G.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <email>riskindrg@guilford.edu</email>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-2"/>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                    <name>
                        <surname>Nosek</surname>
                        <given-names>Brian A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <email>nosek@virginia.edu</email>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-3"/>
                </contrib>
            </contrib-group>
            <aff id="aff-1">University of Virginia, Department of Psychology, Box 400400,
                Charlottesville, VA, 22904, USA</aff>
            <aff id="aff-2">Guilford College, Department of Psychology, Greensboro, NC, 27410,
                USA</aff>
            <aff id="aff-3">Center for Open Science, 210 Ridge McIntire Road, Suite 500,
                Charlottesville, VA, 22911, USA</aff>
            <pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="pub" iso-8601-date="2015-07-23">
                <day>23</day>
                <month>07</month>
                <year>2015</year>
            </pub-date>
            <volume>1</volume>
            <issue>1</issue>
            <elocation-id>1</elocation-id>
            <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Copyright: &#x00A9; 2015 The Author(s)</copyright-statement>
                <copyright-year>2015</copyright-year>
                <license license-type="open-access"
                    xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">
                    <license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the
                        Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 Unported License (CC-BY 3.0), which permits
                        unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the
                        original author and source are credited. See <uri
                            xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/"
                            >http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/</uri>.</license-p>
                </license>
            </permissions>
            <self-uri xlink:href="http://collabra.org/articles/10.1525/collabra.18/"/>
            <abstract>
                <p>Legal rights and cultural attitudes towards lesbian women and gay men have
                    shifted rapidly in the early 21<sup>st</sup> century. Using 683,976 visitors to
                    Project Implicit from February 2006 to August 2013, we investigated whether
                    shifts were also observable in implicit evaluations that occur outside of
                    conscious awareness or control. Similar to public opinion polling, the estimated
                    explicit preference for straight people over lesbian women and gay men was 26%
                    weaker on the last day compared to the first. The estimated implicit preference
                    for straight people declined by 13.4% over the same period. The largest shifts
                    in implicit evaluations occurred among Hispanic, White, female, liberal, and
                    young adult participants; the smallest shifts occurred among Black, Asian, male,
                    conservative, and older adult participants. Societal change in evaluation of
                    lesbian and gay people is not limited to what people are willing and able to
                    report. However, change in implicit evaluation appears to be slower.</p>
            </abstract>
            <kwd-group>
                <kwd>Implicit Association Test</kwd>
                <kwd>culture</kwd>
                <kwd>social psychology</kwd>
                <kwd>implicit social cognition</kwd>
                <kwd>sexual orientation</kwd>
            </kwd-group>
        </article-meta>
    </front>
    <body>
        <p>During the first part of the 21<sup>st</sup> century, the legal rights and social roles
            of lesbian and gay people have been in flux. Positive and complex depictions of lesbian
            and gay television characters have become far more common in the U.S. [<xref
                ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>]. Further, U.S. news media have extensively
            covered the suicides and peer rejection of LGBT adolescents as well as responses like
            Savage&#8217;s <italic>It Gets Better</italic> campaign [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23"
                >23</xref>]. In 2010, the U.S. Congress and President Obama repealed the U.S.
            military&#8217;s Don&#8217;t Ask, Don&#8217;t Tell policy, which had prohibited LGBT
            people from serving openly in the armed forces. Perhaps the most discussed issue was
            change in the legal recognition of same-sex couple relationships. In 2003, marriages
            between two people of the same gender were not legally recognized anywhere in the United
            States. In contrast, as of the end of 2014, 35 states, the District of Columbia, and the
            federal government legally recognize such marriages.</p>
        <p>Accompanying the changes in legal rights, self-reported attitudes towards lesbian and gay
            people have also been shifting [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>]. National
            Gallup polls show that moral approval of lesbian and gay people in the U.S. has
            increased from 44% in 2006 to 59% in 2013 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref><xref
                ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>]. In a worldwide poll, the Pew Global Attitudes
            Project found that in 2003 a slim majority of 51% of respondents felt that homosexuality
            should be accepted by society. By 2013, this number had increased to 60%. In both cases,
            people who expressed positive attitudes towards lesbian and gay people were in the
            minority in the 2000s but constituted the majority of respondents by 2013. Horn (2012)
            presented a multidimensional framework to describe predictors of self-reported
            attitudes. These include participant demographic (e.g., gender) and personality (e.g.,
            gender role attitude) characteristics, as well as perceptions of the target and the type
            of self-report attitude measured. Despite change in self-reported attitudes, these
            predictors have remained relatively consistent across this time period [<xref
                ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>].</p>
        <p>This shift in legal rights and cultural attitudes is dramatic. It prompts a question of
            significant theoretical interest in attitude research: what has changed? Self-reported
            attitudes can shift because people change their minds or because expressing one&#8217;s
            mind becomes fraught with social consequences [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2"
                >2</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>]. It is possible that the shifts
            towards greater positivity toward lesbian women and gay men in past research are merely
            indicators of decreased willingness to express negative attitudes. In other words, are
            these changes in mental representation or have people just become more reluctant to
            admit to bias?</p>
        <p>Implicit measures of evaluation offer an opportunity to test explanations for the
            observed change in attitudes. Should we attribute shifts in reported attitudes to shifts
            in <italic>evaluation</italic>? Or, are we observing shifts in willingness to
                <italic>express</italic> negative evaluations of lesbian and gay people &#8211; due
            to people&#8217;s unwillingness to admit to or endorse those evaluations? Implicit
            measures assess evaluations without requiring an act of introspection and are relatively
            uncontrollable ([<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref><xref ref-type="bibr"
                rid="B17">17</xref>]; and for discussion of interpretation of implicit and explicit
            attitude constructs see [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref><xref ref-type="bibr"
                rid="B5">5</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref><xref ref-type="bibr"
                rid="B19">19</xref>]). If preferences for straight people compared to lesbian women
            and gay men show evidence of change on implicit measures as well as explicit measures,
            this would suggest that evaluations, not just reporting tendencies, are changing.</p>
        <p>The present research used the Implicit Association Test (IAT) to investigate whether
            implicit attitudes towards lesbian and gay people have changed over time. The IAT is a
            computerized reaction time measure that assesses the comparative strength of
            associations between two pairs of concepts. Participants use two keys on a keyboard to
            categorize target stimuli appearing one at a time on the screen as belonging to one of
            two categories (&#8220;Gay people&#8221; or &#8220;Straight people&#8221;) or one of two
            attributes (&#8220;Good&#8221; or &#8220;Bad&#8221;). If people are faster at accurately
            categorizing stimuli when &#8220;Gay people&#8221; and &#8220;Bad&#8221; are paired on
            the same side of the screen (compared to when &#8220;Straight people&#8221; and
            &#8220;Bad&#8221; are paired on the same side of the screen), it suggests that people
            have stronger negative associations with gay people than with straight people. The IAT
            thus can provide a measure of implicit evaluations of lesbian and gay people.</p>
        <p>Moreover, there is considerable interest and evidence for the malleability of implicit
            evaluation in the short term (e.g., [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref><xref
                ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>]), but much less evidence for long-term or
            cultural shifts in evaluation (see [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>] for a
            review). In order to determine the magnitude of change at the cultural level,
            researchers must examine shifts in mean bias across time. Knowing how and when implicit
            attitudes change on a cultural level is vitally important to understanding how long-term
            enduring changes in implicit attitudes occur. When large numbers of individuals
            experience small changes, these changes accumulate into large differences at the
            societal level. Thus, it is important to examine both change on the individual level
            (i.e., the association between date and an individual&#8217;s bias score) as well as
            change in bias over time aggregated across many individuals (i.e., how much the sample
            mean changes over time).</p>
        <p>To date, no researchers have identified any instances of implicit evaluation change on a
            cultural level. Such knowledge may help identify interventions and situations most
            likely to lead to lasting changes in implicit attitude evaluations. In the most similar
            study, Schmidt and Nosek ([<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>];
                <italic>N</italic> = 479,405) found little evidence for change in implicit racial
            preferences for Whites over Blacks between September 2006 and May 2009 that could have
            been attributed to the rise and election of Barack Obama as the first Black U.S.
            president. That lack of an effect was particularly interesting in light of evidence from
            laboratory research, which demonstrated that Obama could operate as a means of shifting
            implicit racial preferences short-term in the lab [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21"
                >21</xref>]. Clearly, short-term malleability in the lab does not always translate
            to long-term social change. Thus, the present research may provide the first opportunity
            to demonstrate evidence of shifting implicit preferences across time on a cultural
            scale.</p>
        <sec sec-type="methods">
            <title>Materials and Method</title>
            <p>Participants self-selected the &#8220;Sexuality IAT&#8221; from a list of available
                IATs after arriving on the Project Implicit demo site at <ext-link
                    ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                    xlink:href="https://implicit.harvard.edu"
                    >https://implicit.harvard.edu</ext-link> and completing informed consent. The
                presentation order of the IAT, explicit measures, and demographics measures was
                randomized. After completing all measures, participants were debriefed with feedback
                on their IAT performance. All data were collected with human subjects approval from
                the University of Virginia.</p>
            <p>Participants were volunteers who visited Project Implicit&#8217;s demonstration site
                and selected the &#8220;Sexuality&#8221; Implicit Association Test (IAT) between
                February 6, 2006 and August 10, 2013, for a total of 7.48 years (2742 days) of data
                collection. February 6, 2006 marked the introduction of demographic items in the
                Sexuality IAT used in this analysis, and August 10, 2013 marked the initiation of
                data analysis for this project. We included only participants who had (a) complete
                data for all key measures and covariates and (b) an overall error rate of less than
                30% or error rates below 40% on any individual block and a latency of 400ms or less
                on fewer than 10% of IAT trials [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref><xref
                    ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>]. We excluded 3.6% of eligible sessions on
                the latter criterion. The final dataset consisted of 683,976 sessions, with a mean
                of 250 (<italic>SD</italic> = 215.23; median = 214) sessions per day. For the final
                complete dataset, the smallest daily sample consisted of 1 session (during website
                downtime), and the largest consisted of 4664 sessions. The middle 80% of daily
                sample sizes ranged from 94 to 424 sessions. There was no evidence of systematic
                variation across time in the number of IAT sessions per day, <italic>b</italic> =
                    &#8211;.<italic>001, t(2729)</italic> = &#8211;.<italic>183, p</italic> =
                    .<italic>86, R<sup>2</sup></italic> &lt; .<italic>0001.</italic></p>
            <p>Participants&#8217; average age was 24.9 years (<italic>SD</italic> = 10.6), and
                62.3% of participants identified as female. Among participants, 70.8 percent
                reported their ethnicity as White (not of Hispanic origin), 6.4% as Asian or Pacific
                Islander, 6.3% as Black (not of Hispanic origin), 5.2% multiracial (Other), 4.7% as
                &#8220;other&#8221; or did not know, 4.6% Hispanic, 1.5% multi-racial (Black and
                White), and 0.6% as American Indian or Alaskan Native. Eighty percent of
                participants identified as heterosexual, 10.4% as lesbian, gay, or homosexual, and
                9.6% as bisexual. Participants were relatively highly educated; 62.5% reported some
                college or an undergraduate college degree, 12.2% were completing or had completed
                an advanced degree, and 25.4% reported a high school education or less. Politically,
                52% of participants identified as liberal, 20.2% conservative, and 27.8% moderate.
                Most participants were U.S. residents (83.2%).</p>
            <p>Below, we report all measures that we analyzed for this study, and manipulations of
                order and procedural conditions for the IAT. Additional measures are available in
                the dataset. Complete codebooks and datafiles are available at: <ext-link
                    ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                    xlink:href="https://osf.io/p7va5/">https://osf.io/p7va5/</ext-link> and
                    <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                    xlink:href="https://osf.io/ctqxo/">https://osf.io/ctqxo/</ext-link>.</p>
            <p><italic>Explicit preferences for straight people compared to lesbian and gay
                    people</italic>. Explicit attitudes for the first half of 2006 were assessed on
                a five-point Likert scale, ranging from <italic>&#8211;</italic>2 &#8220;I strongly
                prefer straight people to gay people&#8221; to +2 &#8220;I strongly prefer gay
                people to straight people.&#8221; Explicit attitudes from the end of 2006 through
                2013 were assessed on a seven-point Likert scale ranging from
                    <italic>&#8211;</italic>3 &#8220;I strongly prefer straight people to gay
                people&#8221; to +3 &#8220;I strongly prefer gay people to straight people.&#8221;
                In both cases, the midpoint represented equal liking of straight and gay people.
                Scores from both scales were Z-transformed and combined into one standardized scale
                retaining the rational zero midpoint of no preference.</p>
            <p><italic>Implicit preferences for straight people compared to lesbian women or gay
                    men</italic>. The IAT is a computerized reaction time measure that assesses the
                comparative strength of associations between two pairs of concepts [<xref
                    ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>].
                Participants use two keys on a keyboard to categorize target stimuli appearing one
                at a time on the screen as belonging to one of four categories (&#8220;Gay
                people&#8221;, &#8220;Straight people&#8221;, &#8220;Good&#8221;,
                &#8220;Bad&#8221;). Average response latencies in categorizing stimuli correctly are
                compared between two response conditions: (1) <italic>Gay people</italic> and
                    <italic>Good</italic> items are categorized with one response key
                (&#8216;e&#8217;) and <italic>Straight people</italic> and <italic>Bad</italic>
                items are categorized with the other (&#8216;i&#8217;); or, (2) <italic>Gay
                    people</italic> and <italic>Bad</italic> items are categorized with one response
                key and <italic>Straight people</italic> and <italic>Good</italic> items are
                categorized with the other. Participants who categorize items faster in the first
                condition compared to the second are said to have an implicit preference for gay
                people compared to straight people.</p>
            <p>The IAT followed the standard 7-block format described in [<xref ref-type="bibr"
                    rid="B13">13</xref>] and followed the same procedure as the sexuality IAT in
                    [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>] that reviewed its psychometric
                properties, variation across demographic groups, and relations with explicit
                measures. Order of the two category pairing conditions was randomized across
                participants, as was whether good items were categorized with either the
                &#8216;e&#8217; or &#8216;i&#8217; key (and bad items with the other key). Target
                stimuli for <italic>Straight people, Good</italic>, and <italic>Bad</italic>
                categories were the same for all participants. Target stimuli for <italic>Gay
                    people</italic> consisted of pictures and words representing either lesbian
                women or gay men. The images consisted of 1) same-sex vs different-sex wedding
                toppers and 2) abstract restroom-style images of either two women, two men, or a
                woman and a man standing side-by-side. Participants were randomly assigned to see
                stimuli representing either lesbian women or gay men. This variation is known to
                shift the main effect such that participants show somewhat weaker implicit
                preferences for straight people over gay people when the <italic>Gay people</italic>
                category is represented with lesbian women compared to gay men ([<xref
                    ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>], Supplement). We computed scores using the
                    <italic>D</italic> algorithm recommended by Greenwald et al. (2003) with
                response latencies recorded for the time used to make the correct response, even if
                an error occurred during the trial.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
            <title>Results</title>
            <p>We tested whether implicit evaluations of lesbian and gay people have changed over
                time, with 683,976 Project Implicit volunteers who participated between February 6,
                2006 and August 10, 2013, for a total of 7.48 years (2742 days) of data collection.
                Overall, participants showed a preference for straight people over gay people both
                implicitly (IAT <italic>D M</italic> = .33, <italic>SD</italic> = .47, Cohen&#8217;s
                    <italic>d</italic> = .70) and explicitly<xref ref-type="fn" rid="n1">1</xref>
                    (<italic>M</italic> = .60, <italic>SD</italic> = 1.26, <italic>d</italic> =
                .48). The implicit and explicit sexuality attitude measures were positively
                correlated, <italic>r</italic>(654,328) = .437, 95% CI [.435, .439]. We standardized
                the IAT and explicit scores, retaining the rational zero midpoint of no preference
                for the remainder of the analyses.<xref ref-type="fn" rid="n2">2</xref></p>
            <sec>
                <title>Examining shifts in sample demographics over time</title>
                <p>Inferring change with cross-sectional data is difficult. A particular inferential
                    limitation would occur if the composition of the sample changed over time and
                    that composition could account for observed shifts in evaluation. We examined
                    shifts in demographics by regressing age, ethnicity, education, sexual
                    orientation, political ideology, gender, and US residency on date of
                    participation. There were slight shifts in demographic representation over the
                    course of data collection (Total R<sup>2</sup> = .015). The largest shifts were
                    for age and education: the sample became slightly younger and more educated over
                        time<xref ref-type="fn" rid="n3">3</xref>. To a lesser extent, the sample
                    became slightly more female, White, conservative, less straight, and more
                    composed of U.S. residents.</p>
                <p>To account for potential influences, the hierarchical regression models<xref
                        ref-type="fn" rid="n4">4</xref> evaluating the effects of date on implicit
                    and explicit preferences first examined the effect of date in isolation, then
                    tested whether the effect survived after adding these demographics to the model
                    as covariates. Finally, we tested whether the effects of date on preferences
                    were moderated by any of the demographic variables. In sum, when date effects on
                    preferences were evaluated within demographic groups, the shift observed in the
                    aggregate analysis persisted, suggesting that the small shifts in demographics
                    over time could not account for the effects of date on implicit or explicit
                    preferences reported next.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec>
                <title>Hierarchical regression evaluating shift in implicit preferences across
                    time</title>
                <p>Though our primary research question is about societal change over time (i.e.,
                    sample mean change over time), we first examined variation in implicit
                    preferences at the individual level. Many factors predict variation in attitudes
                    across individuals &#8211; sex, race, education, political orientation,
                    religiosity, and one&#8217;s own sexual orientation &#8211; so variance
                    accounted for by date of participation should be minor in comparison to these
                    other sources of variation. Nevertheless, any indication of change at the
                    individual level could accumulate to sizable evidence of change at the societal
                    level.</p>
                <p>We regressed IAT score on participation date to determine whether the magnitude
                    of implicit sexuality preferences changed over time from February 2006 to August
                    2013 (see Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>). Date was negatively
                    related with implicit preference for straight people compared to gay people
                    suggesting that the effect has weakened over time. Date accounted for roughly
                    0.1% of the variance in implicit preferences across individuals (R<sup>2</sup> =
                    .0009). In the second step, we added procedural variables for the implicit
                    measure to the model: order of stimuli, gay men vs. lesbian women stimuli, and
                    whether good items were categorized to the right or left. These variables
                    accounted for about 4.2% of the variation in implicit evaluations but did not
                    affect the relationship between date and implicit evaluation.</p>
                <table-wrap id="T1">
                    <label>Table 1</label>
                    <caption>
                        <p>Hierarchical linear regression (<italic>N</italic> = 683,789) predicting
                            implicit preference for straight people compared to lesbian or gay
                            people by date (Step 1), IAT procedural variables (added in Step 2),
                            demographic variables (added in Step 3), and their interactions (added
                            in Step 4).</p>
                    </caption>
                    <table>
                        <tr>
                            <th align="left" valign="top">Predictor</th>
                            <th align="center" valign="top"><italic>df</italic></th>
                            <th align="center" valign="top">&#951;<sup>2</sup><sub>p</sub></th>
                            <th align="center" valign="top"><italic>F</italic></th>
                            <th align="center" valign="top"><italic>p</italic></th>
                            <th align="center" valign="top"><italic>R<sup>2</sup></italic></th>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td colspan="6">
                                <hr/></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top"><italic>Step 1</italic></td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">0.0009</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">Date</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">1</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">0.00087</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">593.92</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">&lt; .0001</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top"/>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top"><italic>Step 2</italic></td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">0.0415</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">Date</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">1</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">0.00105</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">716.57</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">&lt; .0001</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">Side</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">1</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">0.00025</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">173.95</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">&lt; .0001</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">Order</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">1</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">0.01975</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">13778.68</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">&lt; .0001</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">Stimuli</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">1</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">0.02144</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">14982.77</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">&lt; .0001</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top"/>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top"><italic>Step 3</italic></td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">0.2677</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">Date</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">1</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">0.00088</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">601.62</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">&lt; .0001</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">Side</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">1</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">0.00040</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">271.06</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">&lt; .0001</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">Order</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">1</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">0.02541</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">17835.04</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">&lt; .0001</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">Stimuli</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">1</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">0.02748</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">19328.49</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">&lt; .0001</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">Age</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">1</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">0.00165</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">1127.91</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">&lt; .0001</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">Gender</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">1</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">0.02240</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">15673.50</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">&lt; .0001</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">Race</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">7</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">0.01242</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">1228.85</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">&lt; .0001</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">Sexual orientation</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">2</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">0.13337</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">52629.40</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">&lt; .0001</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">Political orientation</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">1</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">0.04846</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">34833.17</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">&lt; .0001</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">Education</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">4</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">0.00459</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">788.44</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">&lt; .0001</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">US Resident</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">1</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">0.00037</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">251.44</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">&lt; .0001</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top"/>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top"><italic>Step 4</italic></td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">0.2679</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">Date</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">1</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">0.00088</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">10.02</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">0.0016</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">Side</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">1</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">0.00040</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">281.27</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">&lt; .0001</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">Order</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">1</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">0.02542</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">17838.72</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">&lt; .0001</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">Stimuli</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">1</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">0.02749</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">19335.74</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">&lt; .0001</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">Age</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">1</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">0.00163</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">1118.38</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">&lt; .0001</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">Gender</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">1</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">0.02244</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">15706.59</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">&lt; .0001</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">Race</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">7</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">0.01240</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">1208.27</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">&lt; .0001</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">Sexual orientation</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">2</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">0.13325</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">52533.89</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">&lt; .0001</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">Political orientation</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">1</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">0.04849</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">34880.86</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">&lt; .0001</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">Education</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">4</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">0.00457</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">783.65</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">&lt; .0001</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">US Resident</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">1</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">0.00038</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">257.54</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">&lt; .0001</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">Date &#215; Side</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">1</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">0.00004</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">25.65</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">&lt; .0001</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">Date &#215; Order</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">1</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">0</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">0.00</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">0.9534</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">Date &#215; Stimuli</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">1</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">0.00002</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">10.81</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">0.0010</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">Date &#215; Age</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">1</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">0.00007</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">45.21</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">&lt; .0001</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">Date &#215; Gender</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">1</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">0.00001</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">4.67</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">0.0307</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">Date &#215; Race</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">7</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">0.00006</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">5.79</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">&lt; .0001</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">Date &#215; Sexual orientation</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">2</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">0.00002</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">5.79</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">0.0031</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">Date &#215; Political orientation</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">1</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">0.00004</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">24.47</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">&lt; .0001</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">Date &#215; Education</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">4</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">0.00001</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">1.63</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">0.1624</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">Date &#215; US Resident</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">1</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">0</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">0.42</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">0.5146</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                        </tr>
                    </table>
                </table-wrap>
                <p>In the third step, we added demographic variables to the model: sexual
                    orientation, political ideology, gender, race/ethnicity, age, education, and
                    U.S. residency. As expected, these variables substantially increased the
                    model&#8217;s prediction of variation in implicit preferences to 26.8%. In other
                    words, individual differences in identity account for much more variation in
                    implicit preferences than the date they completed the measure.
                    Participants&#8217; sexual orientation and political ideology were particularly
                    predictive. However, including demographic characteristics did not substantially
                    reduce the effect of date predicting implicit preferences.</p>
                <p>Finally, in the fourth step, we added tests of moderation: date (mean centered)
                    interacting with each of the procedural and demographics variables entered in
                    steps 2 and 3. These interactions added very little additional prediction of
                    implicit preferences to the model (change in model R<sup>2</sup> = .0002), and
                    did not qualify date predicting implicit preferences.</p>
                <p>In sum, we observed a very small effect of date on implicit preferences that
                    survived the inclusion of many covariates and moderating terms. It is not
                    surprising that at the individual level, demographic variables are far superior
                    predictors of variation in implicit preferences than which date the participant
                    completed the implicit measure. Substantial individual differences in implicit
                    preferences persist over the timespan across sexual orientation, political
                    ideology, and other variables. On an individual basis, time is a trivial
                    predictor of implicit preferences compared to those identities. While the gaps
                    between gay and straight people and liberals and conservatives may persist
                    across time, the small date effect suggests that the entire culture may be
                    shifting toward more positive evaluations of gay men and lesbians. In other
                    words, if everyone develops more positive attitudes toward gay men and lesbians,
                    then the variation across individuals by demographic factors will be preserved,
                    making date a small contributor in accounting for variation across individuals,
                    while still demonstrating a substantial societal shift.</p>
                <p>Estimating the magnitude of change at the cultural level requires examining how
                    the mean is shifting across time. Many small effects at the level of the
                    individual may add up to large cumulative effects at the cultural level. To
                    examine cultural change, we computed estimated effect sizes for the sample as a
                    whole on the first and final days of data collection (see Table <xref
                        ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>). For these estimates, we predicted
                    standardized IAT <italic>D</italic>-scores for Day 1 and Day 2742 of data
                    collection, calculated from the hierarchical regression analyses presented here.
                    The effect size for date corresponds to an overall decline in the estimated
                    effect size of <italic>d</italic> = .77 on Day 1 of the data collection to a
                        <italic>d</italic> = .67 on Day 2742 (point estimate delta = &#8211;.103).
                    Descriptive data for the mean standardized IAT <italic>D</italic>-scores for
                    each month from 2006 to 2013 can be seen in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1"
                        >1</xref>. In a separate analysis (see SI Appendix), we also tested for
                    non-linear effects of time and found support for a quadratic effect in addition
                    to the linear effect (R<sup>2</sup> = .0013) suggesting that the rate of change
                    accelerated slightly over the time period. In sum, across the nearly 7.5 years
                    of data collection, the mean implicit preference for straight people over gay
                    people declined by 13.4%, a notable decline.</p>
                <table-wrap id="T2">
                    <label>Table 2</label>
                    <caption>
                        <p>Hierarchical linear regression (<italic>N</italic> = 683,789) predicting
                            explicit preference for straight people compared to lesbian or gay
                            people by date (Step 1), demographic variables (added in Step 2), and
                            their interactions (added in Step 3).</p>
                    </caption>
                    <table>
                        <tr>
                            <th align="left" valign="top">Predictor</th>
                            <th align="center" valign="top"><italic>df</italic></th>
                            <th align="center" valign="top">&#951;<sup>2</sup><sub>p</sub></th>
                            <th align="center" valign="top"><italic>F</italic></th>
                            <th align="center" valign="top"><italic>p</italic></th>
                            <th align="center" valign="top"><italic>R<sup>2</sup></italic></th>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td colspan="6">
                                <hr/></td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top"><italic>Step 1</italic></td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">.0017</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">Date</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">1</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">0.0017</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">1086.1</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">&lt; .0001</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top"/>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top"><italic>Step 2</italic></td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">.3251</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">Date</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">1</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">0.00143</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">934.89</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">&lt; .0001</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">Age</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">1</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">0</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">6.87</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">&lt; .0001</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">Gender</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">1</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">0.06065</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">42245.98</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">&lt; .0001</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">Race</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">7</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">0.00888</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">837.78</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">&lt; .0001</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">Sexual orientation</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">2</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">0.15620</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">103850.00</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">&lt; .0001</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">Political orientation</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">1</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">0.10497</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">76738.04</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">&lt; .0001</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">Education</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">4</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">0.00040</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">65.21</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">&lt; .0001</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">US Resident</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">1</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">0.00001</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">6.75</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">0.1000</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top"/>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top"><italic>Step 3</italic></td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">.3261</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">Date</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">1</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">0.00143</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">28.02</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">&lt; .0001</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">Age</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">1</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">0.00001</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">7.89</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">0.0050</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">Gender</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">1</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">0.06058</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">39209.61</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">&lt; .0001</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">Race</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">7</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">0.00891</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">733.31</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">&lt; .0001</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">Sexual orientation</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">2</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">0.15650</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">56799.35</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">&lt; .0001</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">Political orientation</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">1</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">0.10519</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">72035.93</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">&lt; .0001</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">Education</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">4</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">0.00041</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">75.25</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">&lt; .0001</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">US Resident</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">1</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">0.00001</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">19.56</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">0.1000</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">Date &#215; Age</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">1</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">0</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">0.02</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">0.8842</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">Date &#215; Gender</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">1</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">0.00003</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">19.47</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">&lt; .0001</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">Date &#215; Race</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">7</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">0.00002</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">2.26</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">0.0267</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">Date &#215; Sexual orientation</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">2</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">0.00067</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">219.77</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">&lt; .0001</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">Date &#215; Political orientation</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">1</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">0.00016</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">105.02</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">&lt; .0001</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">Date &#215; Education</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">4</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">0.00011</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">17.37</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">&lt; .0001</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" valign="top">Date &#215; US Resident</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">1</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">0.00008</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">50.47</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top">&lt; .0001</td>
                            <td align="right" valign="top"/>
                        </tr>
                    </table>
                </table-wrap>
                <table-wrap id="T3">
                    <label>Table 3</label>
                    <caption>
                        <p>Predicted standardized IAT D-scores for Day 1 and Day 2742 of data
                            collection calculated from hierarchical regression analyses,
                            illustrating demographic moderators of shifts in implicit preferences
                            across time.</p>
                    </caption>
                    <table>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left">
                                <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                                    xlink:href="figures/Table03_web.png"/>
                            </td>
                        </tr>
                    </table>
                </table-wrap>
                <fig id="F1">
                    <label>Figure 1</label>
                    <caption>
                        <p>Mean daily implicit preference for straight people over gay people from
                            February 2006 to August 2013 with 7-days moving average.</p>
                    </caption>
                    <graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                        xlink:href="figures/Fig01_web.png"/>
                </fig>
            </sec>
            <sec>
                <title>Hierarchical regression evaluating shift in explicit preferences across
                    time</title>
                <p>We used the same analysis plan to evaluate shifts in explicit preferences across
                    time, excluding the step adding IAT procedural variables to the model. In the
                    first step, we regressed participation date on explicit preferences (see Table
                        <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>). Date was negatively related to
                    explicit preferences for straight people compared to gay people suggesting that
                    the effect has weakened over time. Date accounted for about 0.17% of the
                    variance in explicit preferences across individuals (R<sup>2</sup> = .0017).</p>
                <p>In the second step, adding demographics to the model substantially increased the
                    model&#8217;s prediction of variation in explicit attitudes to 33%. As with
                    implicit attitudes, participants&#8217; sexual orientation and political
                    ideology accounted for the most variation. Even so, the effect of date
                    predicting explicit preferences persisted. In the third step, adding
                    interactions between date and the demographics added little additional
                    prediction of explicit preferences to the model. Furthermore, these variables
                    did not qualify the effect of date predicting explicit preferences.</p>
                <p>As noted above, change at the cultural level is indicated by the mean change over
                    time. We therefore computed regression estimated effect sizes for the sample as
                    a whole on the first and final days of data collection. The effect size for date
                    corresponds to a decline in estimated effect size from <italic>d</italic> = .54
                    on day 1 of the data collection to a <italic>d</italic> = .40 on day 2742 (Point
                    estimate delta = &#8211;.139). In a separate analysis (see SI Appendix), we also
                    tested for non-linear effects of time and found support for a quadratic effect
                    in addition to a linear effect of time (R<sup>2</sup> = .0030), suggesting that
                    the rate of change accelerated slightly over the time period.</p>
                <p>In sum, paralleling the results for implicit preferences, we found an effect of
                    date on explicit attitudes that survived the inclusion of many covariates and
                    moderating terms. All told, across the nearly 7.5 years of data collection, the
                    mean explicit preference for straight people compared to gay people declined by
                    26% at the cultural level. This effect was approximately twice the size of the
                    cultural shift observed using implicit measures.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec>
                <title>Demographic moderators of shifts in implicit preferences across time</title>
                <p>We conducted exploratory analyses to learn whether some demographic groups showed
                    more evidence of shifting implicit preferences over time than others (i.e., the
                    moderation effects in Step 4 of the hierarchical regression). Table <xref
                        ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref> displays predicted standardized IAT
                        <italic>D</italic>-scores for Day 1 and Day 2742 of data collection,
                    calculated from the hierarchical regression analyses presented above. Predicted
                    scores for the first and last day were used in place of raw scores to represent
                    the estimated trend in preferences across the time period. Positive point
                    estimates represent pro-straight implicit preference, and negative point
                    estimates represent pro-gay implicit preference, with a rational zero
                    midpoint.</p>
                <p>Overall, race/ethnicity, age, political ideology were the strongest moderators.
                    White and Hispanic people showed greater shifts than Asian and Black people,
                    younger adults showed greater shifts than older adults, and liberals showed
                    greater shifts than conservatives. Women showed slightly greater shifts in
                    implicit preferences than men. Shifting implicit preferences were not confined
                    to straight people; straight, bisexual, and lesbian or gay people all showed
                    moderate shifts in implicit preferences during this time period, with bisexual
                    people showing evidence of the largest shifts (see Figure <xref ref-type="fig"
                        rid="F1">1</xref>). Overall, attitudes towards lesbian women shifted more
                    than attitudes towards gay men. There was little evidence for differential
                    change as a function of education or U.S. residency.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec>
                <title>Demographic moderators of shifts in explicit preferences across time</title>
                <p>We conducted similar exploratory analyses for explicit preferences (i.e., the
                    moderation effects in Step 3 of the hierarchical regression). Overall, sexual
                    orientation, political ideology, education, and U.S. residency were the largest
                    moderators. Lesbian and gay participants reported weaker explicit preferences
                    for gay people over straight people over time, whereas straight participants
                    reported weaker explicit preferences for straight people over gay people over
                    time. In other words, both groups reported weaker absolute preferences on the
                    basis of sexual orientation over time. Conservatives shifted more than liberals,
                    U.S. residents shifted more than non-U.S. residents, and less-educated people
                    shifted more than highly educated people (college degree or higher). We observed
                    a smaller effect for gender and race, with men shifting more than women and
                    Black people shifting slightly more than White people. There was little evidence
                    for differential change as a function of age.</p>
            </sec>
        </sec>
        <sec>
            <title>Discussion</title>
            <p>The cultural shift in legal rights and attitudes toward gay men and lesbians is not
                limited to what people are willing and able to report on explicit measures. In a
                very large sample collected between 2006 and 2013, we replicated evidence from
                public opinion polls for change over time in explicit attitudes towards lesbian and
                gay people. For the first time, we contributed evidence that this attitude shift has
                occurred implicitly, as well. This is the first documented evidence for a cultural
                shift in implicit evaluations about any topic. Implicit preference for straight
                people over gay people declined overall by 13.4% from 2007 to 2013, and explicit
                preferences declined by 26% during that same period. Notably, the shift in explicit
                preferences was about twice the size of the shift in implicit preferences in this
                sample. This suggests that change is more rapid in evaluations that people report
                willingly than those that may operate outside of conscious awareness or conscious
                control.</p>
            <p>Nearly all demographic groups showed weakening of implicit preferences for straight
                people over gay people over time, with the greatest changes occurring among
                Hispanic, White, female, liberal, and young adult participants. The smallest changes
                in implicit evaluations occurred among Black, Asian, male, conservative, and older
                adult participants. Interestingly, however, the relative magnitude of change was
                largely opposite for explicit preferences. Although nearly all groups reported
                weaker explicit preferences for straight people over gay people, shifts in explicit
                preferences were greatest among straight, male, conservative, Black, and
                less-educated participants. These are also the groups that held the strongest
                overall preferences for straight people. The two findings together offer a
                speculative interpretation: substantial explicit change may occur first and perhaps
                enable the slower implicit change that occurs later. Here, increases in explicit
                positivity toward gay men and lesbians may have already occurred among women and
                liberals prior to the assessed time period, setting the stage for later change in
                implicit preferences. Men and conservatives, however, may be currently undergoing
                explicit change, which could accelerate implicit change in the future. With the
                present data, however, this possibility is only speculation.</p>
            <p>Evidence for the changing preferences of gay men and lesbian women furthers this
                speculation. Implicitly, these groups showed more substantial increases than
                straight participants in their positive evaluations of gay people compared to
                straight people. Explicitly, however, gay participants&#8217; reported preferences
                for gay compared to straight people weakened across the time period. That is,
                implicit and explicit changes were moving in opposite directions. It is as if
                explicit pro-gay preferences had become relatively extreme and were now becoming
                more moderate in the face of an increasingly tolerant culture, while implicit
                pro-gay preferences were continuing to strengthen, indicating the slow cumulative
                change over time. In the coming epoch, implicit preferences among lesbian women and
                gay men may likewise become more moderate, following the explicit trends. In sum,
                might explicit change be a leading indicator of eventual implicit change? Systematic
                investigation of this possibility is left to future research.</p>
            <p>The current study has limitations. In particular, it is a cross-sectional comparison
                of a non-representative sample of the U.S. and world populations who may be younger
                and less likely to identify themselves as male, conservative, or straight than the
                general population. Given that we do not have experimental control over the
                sampling, we cannot eliminate the possibility that an undetected selection effect is
                responsible for the apparent shift. However, this seems unlikely, as the effects are
                robust to controlling for the demographic variables available in the dataset, and
                our explicit data mirrors attitudinal shifts observed in Gallup and other
                representative polling. Also, the IAT stimulus set featured symbolic representations
                of gay and lesbian couples rather than individuals, and it may be difficult to
                compare relative change between the implicit and explicit measures due to variance
                in the measures&#8217; estimates. Finally, we were not able to examine religion as a
                potential moderator due to lack of data spanning the time period of interest.
                However, one strength is that we conducted daily assessments of implicit and
                explicit preferences towards gay and lesbian people, across more than seven years,
                with a massive sample, controlling for demographic characteristics. It is
                reasonable, but not definitive, to interpret the observed decline over time in
                preferences for straight people over gay people as indicating actual cultural
                change. Notably, despite the overall decline, participants still exhibited
                pronounced pro-straight preferences at the end of the time period. It would be
                useful to accumulate longitudinal evidence on representative samples in order to
                confirm this effect and provide parameter estimates for the magnitude of change
                across the culture.</p>
            <p>A notable feature of this shift is that while we observed large shifts at the
                cultural level, the change in attitude for any single individual was trivial in
                effect size. The passage of time, and the cultural change occurring with it,
                accounts for an extremely small amount of a single person&#8217;s implicit and
                explicit preferences, especially when compared to features of their identity such as
                sexual orientation and politics. What makes this observed change important is the
                fact that it is occurring across the entire sample, and across demographic
                categories, indicating a <italic>cultural shift</italic> in evaluation of lesbian
                and gay people. The tiny change for one individual accumulates into a substantial
                cultural effect expressed in all individuals (13.4% decline for implicit preferences
                and 26% decline for explicit preferences). For comparison, the effect size of time
                observed in this study was one hundred times greater than that found by Schmidt and
                colleagues (2010) when they examined change in implicit racial attitudes before and
                after President Obama&#8217;s election. It is unclear whether a large change in a
                few people or a small change in everyone ultimately has a more substantial impact on
                society. We anticipate that most social change starts with large attitude changes
                within a subset of society and eventually ripples out to produce small changes in
                all members of society [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>]. In the early
                    21<sup>st</sup> century, we appear to be bearing witness to this effect for
                evaluations of lesbian women and gay men.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
            <title>Conflict of Interest Declaration</title>
            <p>Nosek is an officer of Project Implicit Inc., a non-profit organization that includes
                in its mission &#8220;To develop and deliver methods for investigating and applying
                phenomena of implicit social cognition, including especially phenomena of implicit
                bias based on age, race, gender or other factors.&#8221;</p>
        </sec>
    </body>
    <back>
        <sec>
            <title>Authors&#8217; Note</title>
            <p>Correspondence can be sent to: Erin Westgate, University of Virginia, Department of
                Psychology, Box 400400, Charlottesville, VA 22904, USA. Email: <ext-link
                    ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                    xlink:href="mailto:ecw4za@virginia.edu">ecw4za@virginia.edu</ext-link>. The
                authors of the paper contributed as follows: Designed research: B.N., E.W, R.R.;
                Analyzed data: E.W., R.R.; Wrote paper: E.W., R.R., B.N. We report all data
                exclusions, manipulations, and how we determined our sample sizes. We report all
                measures that were analyzed for this study. Additional measures are available in the
                dataset, and codebooks and data are available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri"
                    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://osf.io/p7va5/"
                    >https://osf.io/p7va5/</ext-link>. Additional years of data are available here:
                    <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                    xlink:href="https://osf.io/ctqxo/">https://osf.io/ctqxo/</ext-link>. This
                research was supported by Project Implicit.</p>
        </sec>
        <fn-group>
            <fn id="n1">
                <p>We report these descriptive statistics for explicit attitudes for the 7-point
                    self-report measure in use between December 2006 and August 2013. Descriptive
                    statistics for the 5-point self-report measure are available in the SI Appendix.
                    Standardized scores for the 5- and 7-point scales are used in all subsequent
                    analyses, covering the entire period of data collection.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="n2">
                <p>IAT scores were standardized independently for a few variations of the task
                    procedure that were presented during the time period. Details of the original
                    means and standardizing procedure are available in the SI Appendix.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="n3">
                <p>Details regarding this regression analysis are available in Table <xref
                        ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref> of the SI Appendix.</p>
            </fn>
            <fn id="n4">
                <p>Auto-correlation in the data is a potential concern when analyzing change across
                    many consecutive days in a single time period. We observed minimal
                    auto-correlation in the present data. See SI for additional information and
                    analyses.</p>
            </fn>
        </fn-group>
        <ref-list>
            <ref id="B1">
                <label>1</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name>
                            <surname>Banaji</surname>
                            <given-names>MR</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <person-group person-group-type="editor">
                        <name>
                            <surname>Roediger</surname>
                            <given-names>HL</given-names>
                            <suffix>III</suffix>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Nairne</surname>
                            <given-names>JS</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Neath</surname>
                            <given-names>IE</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Surprenant</surname>
                            <given-names>AM</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <chapter-title>Implicit attitudes can be measured</chapter-title>
                    <source>The nature of remembering: Essays in honor of Robert G. Crowder</source>
                    <year iso-8601-date="2001">2001</year>
                    <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>
                    <publisher-name>American Psychological Association</publisher-name>
                    <fpage>117</fpage>
                    <lpage>150</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B2">
                <label>2</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name>
                            <surname>Dasgupta</surname>
                            <given-names>N</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Riviera</surname>
                            <given-names>L</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <article-title>When social context matters: The influence of long-term contact
                        and short-term exposure to admired out-group members on implicit attitudes
                        and behavioral intentions</article-title>
                    <source>Social Cognition</source>
                    <year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year>
                    <volume>26</volume>
                    <fpage>112</fpage>
                    <lpage>123</lpage>
                    <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1521/soco.2008.26.1.112</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B3">
                <label>3</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="webpage">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <collab>Gallup</collab>
                    </person-group>
                    <article-title>&#8220;Regardless of whether or not you think it should be legal,
                        for each one, please tell me whether you personally believe that in general
                        it is morally acceptable or morally wrong. How about homosexual
                        behavior?&#8221;</article-title>
                    <source>[Survey report] in Gay and Lesbian Rights</source>
                    <year iso-8601-date="2006">2006</year>
                    <month>May</month>
                    <day>8&#8211;11</day>
                    <comment>Retrieved from
                            <uri>http://www.gallup.com/poll/1651/gay-lesbian-rights.aspx</uri></comment>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B4">
                <label>4</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="webpage">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <collab>Gallup</collab>
                    </person-group>
                    <article-title>&#8220;Regardless of whether or not you think it should be legal,
                        for each one, please tell me whether you personally believe that in general
                        it is morally acceptable or morally wrong. How about gay or lesbian
                        relations?&#8221;</article-title>
                    <source>[Survey report] in Gay and Lesbian Rights</source>
                    <year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year>
                    <month>May</month>
                    <day>2&#8211;7</day>
                    <comment>Retrieved from
                            <uri>http://www.gallup.com/poll/1651/gay-lesbian-rights.aspx</uri></comment>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B5">
                <label>5</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name>
                            <surname>Gawronski</surname>
                            <given-names>B</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Bodenhausen</surname>
                            <given-names>GV</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <article-title>Associative and propositional processes in evaluation: an
                        integrative review of implicit and explicit attitude change</article-title>
                    <source>Psychological Bulletin</source>
                    <year iso-8601-date="2006">2006</year>
                    <volume>132</volume>
                    <fpage>692</fpage>
                    <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/0033-2909.132.5.692</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B6">
                <label>6</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name>
                            <surname>Greenwald</surname>
                            <given-names>AG</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>McGhee</surname>
                            <given-names>DE</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Schwartz</surname>
                            <given-names>JL</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <article-title>Measuring individual differences in implicit cognition: the
                        implicit association test</article-title>
                    <source>Journal of Personality and Social Psychology</source>
                    <year iso-8601-date="1998">1998</year>
                    <volume>74</volume>
                    <fpage>1464</fpage>
                    <lpage>1480</lpage>
                    <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/0022-3514.74.6.1464</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B7">
                <label>7</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name>
                            <surname>Greenwald</surname>
                            <given-names>AG</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Nosek</surname>
                            <given-names>BA</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Banaji</surname>
                            <given-names>MR</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <article-title>Understanding and using the implicit association test: I. An
                        improved scoring algorithm</article-title>
                    <source>Journal of Personality and Social Psychology</source>
                    <year iso-8601-date="2003">2003</year>
                    <volume>85</volume>
                    <fpage>197</fpage>
                    <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/0022-3514.85.2.197</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B8">
                <label>8</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name>
                            <surname>Horn</surname>
                            <given-names>SS</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <person-group person-group-type="editor">
                        <name>
                            <surname>Patterson</surname>
                            <given-names>CJ</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>D&#8217;Augelli</surname>
                            <given-names>A</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <chapter-title>Attitudes about sexual orientation</chapter-title>
                    <source>Handbook of Psychology and Sexual Orientation</source>
                    <year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year>
                    <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
                    <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>
                    <fpage>239</fpage>
                    <lpage>251</lpage>
                    <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/acprof:oso/9780199765218.003.0017</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B9">
                <label>9</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="webpage">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name>
                            <surname>Kane</surname>
                            <given-names>M</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Gouttebroze</surname>
                            <given-names>M</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Townsend</surname>
                            <given-names>M</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <source>Network responsibility index</source>
                    <year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year>
                    <comment>Retrieved from <uri>http://www.glaad.org/</uri></comment>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B10">
                <label>10</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name>
                            <surname>Lai</surname>
                            <given-names>CK</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Hoffman</surname>
                            <given-names>KM</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Nosek</surname>
                            <given-names>BA</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <article-title>Reducing implicit prejudice</article-title>
                    <source>Social and Personality Psychology Compass</source>
                    <year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year>
                    <volume>7</volume>
                    <fpage>315</fpage>
                    <lpage>330</lpage>
                    <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/spc3.12023</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B11">
                <label>11</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name>
                            <surname>Lai</surname>
                            <given-names>CK</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Marini</surname>
                            <given-names>M</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Lehr</surname>
                            <given-names>SA</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Cerrutl</surname>
                            <given-names>C</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Shin</surname>
                            <given-names>JE</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Joy-Gaba</surname>
                            <given-names>JA</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <etal/>
                    </person-group>
                    <article-title>Reducing implicit racial preferences: I. A comparative
                        investigation of 17 interventions</article-title>
                    <source>Journal of Experimental Psychology: General</source>
                    <year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year>
                    <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/a0036260</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B12">
                <label>12</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name>
                            <surname>Nosek</surname>
                            <given-names>BA</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Banaji</surname>
                            <given-names>MR</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Jost</surname>
                            <given-names>JT</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <person-group person-group-type="editor">
                        <name>
                            <surname>Jost</surname>
                            <given-names>JT</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Kay</surname>
                            <given-names>AC</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Thorisdottir</surname>
                            <given-names>H</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <chapter-title>The politics of intergroup attitudes</chapter-title>
                    <source>Social and Psychological Bases of Ideology and System
                        Justification</source>
                    <year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year>
                    <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
                    <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>
                    <fpage>480</fpage>
                    <lpage>506</lpage>
                    <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/acprof:oso/9780195320916.003.020</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B13">
                <label>13</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name>
                            <surname>Nosek</surname>
                            <given-names>BA</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Greenwald</surname>
                            <given-names>AG</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Banaji</surname>
                            <given-names>MR</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <article-title>Understanding and using the Implicit Association Test: II. Method
                        variables and construct validity</article-title>
                    <source>Personality and Social Psychology Bulletin</source>
                    <year iso-8601-date="2005">2005</year>
                    <volume>31</volume>
                    <fpage>166</fpage>
                    <lpage>180</lpage>
                    <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0146167204271418</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B14">
                <label>14</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name>
                            <surname>Nosek</surname>
                            <given-names>BA</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Greenwald</surname>
                            <given-names>AG</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Banaji</surname>
                            <given-names>MR</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <person-group person-group-type="editor">
                        <name>
                            <surname>Bargh</surname>
                            <given-names>JA</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <chapter-title>The Implicit Association Test at age 7: A methodological and
                        conceptual review</chapter-title>
                    <source>Social psychology and the Unconscious: The Automaticity of Higher Mental
                        Processes</source>
                    <year iso-8601-date="2007">2007</year>
                    <publisher-loc>Philadelphia</publisher-loc>
                    <publisher-name>Psychology Press</publisher-name>
                    <fpage>265</fpage>
                    <lpage>292</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B15">
                <label>15</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name>
                            <surname>Nosek</surname>
                            <given-names>BA</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Hansen</surname>
                            <given-names>JJ</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <article-title>The associations in our heads belong to us: Searching for
                        attitudes and knowledge in implicit evaluation</article-title>
                    <source>Cognition &amp; Emotion</source>
                    <year iso-8601-date="2008">2008</year>
                    <volume>22</volume>
                    <fpage>553</fpage>
                    <lpage>594</lpage>
                    <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/02699930701438186</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B16">
                <label>16</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name>
                            <surname>Nosek</surname>
                            <given-names>BA</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Hawkins</surname>
                            <given-names>CB</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Frazier</surname>
                            <given-names>RS</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <article-title>Implicit social cognition: From measures to
                        mechanisms</article-title>
                    <source>Trends in Cognitive Sciences</source>
                    <year iso-8601-date="2011">2011</year>
                    <volume>15</volume>
                    <fpage>152</fpage>
                    <lpage>159</lpage>
                    <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tics.2011.01.005</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B17">
                <label>17</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name>
                            <surname>Nosek</surname>
                            <given-names>BA</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Hawkins</surname>
                            <given-names>CB</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Frazier</surname>
                            <given-names>RS</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <person-group person-group-type="editor">
                        <name>
                            <surname>Fiske</surname>
                            <given-names>S</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Macrae</surname>
                            <given-names>CN</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <chapter-title>Implicit social cognition</chapter-title>
                    <source>Handbook of Social Cognition</source>
                    <year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year>
                    <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
                    <publisher-name>Sage</publisher-name>
                    <fpage>31</fpage>
                    <lpage>53</lpage>
                    <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4135/9781446247631.n3</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B18">
                <label>18</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name>
                            <surname>Nosek</surname>
                            <given-names>BA</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Smyth</surname>
                            <given-names>FL</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Hansen</surname>
                            <given-names>JJ</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Devos</surname>
                            <given-names>T</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Lindner</surname>
                            <given-names>NM</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Ranganath</surname>
                            <given-names>KA</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Banaji</surname>
                            <given-names>MR</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <etal/>
                    </person-group>
                    <article-title>Pervasiveness and correlates of implicit attitudes and
                        stereotypes</article-title>
                    <source>European Review of Social Psychology</source>
                    <year iso-8601-date="2007">2007</year>
                    <volume>18</volume>
                    <fpage>36</fpage>
                    <lpage>88</lpage>
                    <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/10463280701489053</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B19">
                <label>19</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name>
                            <surname>Olson</surname>
                            <given-names>MA</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Fazio</surname>
                            <given-names>RH</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <article-title>Reducing the influence of extrapersonal associations on the
                        Implicit Association Test: personalizing the IAT</article-title>
                    <source>Journal of personality and social psychology</source>
                    <year iso-8601-date="2004">2004</year>
                    <volume>86</volume>
                    <issue>5</issue>
                    <fpage>653</fpage>
                    <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/0022-3514.86.5.653</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B20">
                <label>20</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name>
                            <surname>Petty</surname>
                            <given-names>RE</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Brinol</surname>
                            <given-names>P</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <person-group person-group-type="editor">
                        <name>
                            <surname>Gawronski</surname>
                            <given-names>B</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Payne</surname>
                            <given-names>BK</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <chapter-title>Attitude structure and change: Implications for implicit
                        measures</chapter-title>
                    <source>Handbook of implicit social cognition: Measurement, theory, and
                        applications</source>
                    <year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year>
                    <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
                    <publisher-name>Guilford Press</publisher-name>
                    <fpage>335</fpage>
                    <lpage>52</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B21">
                <label>21</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name>
                            <surname>Plant</surname>
                            <given-names>EA</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Devine</surname>
                            <given-names>PG</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Cox</surname>
                            <given-names>WTL</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Columb</surname>
                            <given-names>C</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Miller</surname>
                            <given-names>SL</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Goplen</surname>
                            <given-names>J</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Peruche</surname>
                            <given-names>BM</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <article-title>The Obama effect: Decreasing implicit prejudice and
                        stereotyping</article-title>
                    <source>Journal of Experimental Social Psychology</source>
                    <year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year>
                    <volume>45</volume>
                    <fpage>961</fpage>
                    <lpage>964</lpage>
                    <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jesp.2009.04.018</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B22">
                <label>22</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name>
                            <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                            <given-names>K</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name>
                            <surname>Nosek</surname>
                            <given-names>BA</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <article-title>Implicit (and explicit) racial attitudes barely changed during
                        Barack Obama&#8217;s presidential campaign and early
                        presidency</article-title>
                    <source>Journal of Experimental Social Psychology</source>
                    <year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year>
                    <volume>46</volume>
                    <fpage>308</fpage>
                    <lpage>314</lpage>
                    <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jesp.2009.12.003</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="B23">
                <label>23</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="newspaper">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name>
                            <surname>Stelter</surname>
                            <given-names>B</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <article-title>Campaign offers to help gay youth</article-title>
                    <source>The New York Times</source>
                    <year iso-8601-date="2010">2010</year>
                    <month>October</month>
                    <day>18</day>
                    <comment>Retrieved from <uri>www.nytimes.com</uri></comment>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
        </ref-list>
        <sec>
            <title>Peer review comments</title>
            <p><bold>The author(s) of this paper chose the Open Review option, and the peer review
                    comments are available at:</bold>
                <uri>http://dx.doi.org/10.1525/collabra.18.opr</uri></p>
        </sec>
    </back>
</article>
